OK, uh, anyone got the result?
嗯，有人知道结果了吗？
64, not correct.
64 不正确。
So let's see how we can get the result to be 64.
咱们来看看如何让结果变为 64，说法更自然易懂。
OK, we can go back to the previous slide.
好的，我们可以回到上一页幻灯片。
OK, at this part, right?
好的，这部分对吧？
So we start from this row, 1 can be represented as 13.
我们从这一行开始，1 可以表示为 13。
So 13 minus 3 times 4, and this 3, 13 minus 3 is minus 4 times
所以 13 减去 3 乘以 4，这个 3，13 减去 3 等于负 4 乘以
3 is some combination of 16 and 13.
3 是由 16 和 13 组合而成。
16 minus 13, so this 5 times 13 minus 4 times 16.
16 减去 13，因此这个数是 5 乘以 13 减去 4 乘以 16。
OK, and this 13 can be represented as some combination
好的，这个 13 可以表示为某种组合（更自然、更易理解的翻译）
of 5 times 13 is 93 minus 5 times 16.
5 乘以 13 等于 93，减去 5 乘以 16。
Minus 4 times 16, so this 5 times 93, 1.
减去 4 乘以 16，然后是 5 乘以 93，1。
This 25 minus 4, this is 29 times 16.
这 25 减去 4 等于 29，再乘以 16。
OK, we want to get modular inverse of 16, mod 93.
好的，我们要计算 16 除以 93 的模逆元。
So both sides, we take mod 93, so this part is 0,
因此，双方都进行 93 的模运算，所以这一部分的结果是 0，
and this part, that means this is minus 29,
这一部分表示这是减去 29，翻译得更加自然易懂
is modular inverse of 16.
是 16 的模逆数
So this is congruent to 93 minus 29.
这与 93 减去 29 的结果一致。
So this equals 64 mod 93.
这等于 64 除以 93 的余数，表达得比较直接。
So this is x value, right?
这就是 x 值，没错吧？
So 64 is the modular inverse of 15 mod 93.
64 是 15 除以 93 的模数，即模逆元。
OK, any questions, comments?
好的，有什么问题或意见吗？
So this result is 64.
这个结果为 64。
OK, now we go to part 3.
好的，现在我们开始第三部分。
So part 3, we'll study the prime numbers.
第三部分，我们将学习质数。
From prime numbers, we will learn the Fermat theorem,
从质数中，我们将学习费马定理，让我们一起来探究吧
and then we'll continue with the Euler's theorem.
然后我们继续讲解欧拉定理。
No problem.
没有任何问题
But prime numbers are those numbers with dividers of 1 and itself,
但素数是这样的数，它们的因数只有 1 和它自己，这样的描述更为自然易懂
just like 2, 3, 5, 7, and 11.
就像 2、3、5、7 和 11 那样。
All the numbers are called to be composite numbers, that's 4 and 6.
所有数字都被称作合数，即 4 和 6。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
And we have the fundamental theorem of arithmetic.
我们有算术的基本定理。
That means any integer to be bigger than 1 can be factored in a unique way,
这意味着任何大于 1 的整数都可以以独特的方式分解，这样的表述更为自然和易懂
as a equals p1 to the a1 times p2 to the a2 times pt to the at.
作为 a 等于 p1 的 a1 次方，p2 的 a2 次方，pt 的 at 次方的乘积。
So p1 is more than p2, it's more than pt.
因此，p1 大于 p2，甚至比 pt 还要大。
Those are the prime numbers, and where each ai is part integer,
这些是质数，其中每个 ai 都是部分整数，翻译得更加自然和易懂
so a1, a2 are at the exponent part.
因此，a1 和 a2 位于指数部分。
For example, 24 can be factored as 2 to the 3 times 3 to the 1, right?
例如，24 可以分解为 2 的三次方乘以 3 的一次方，这样的说法对吧？
Two prime numbers to the exponent to be 3 and 1.
两个质数的指数分别是 3 和 1。
Okay, here we have all the primes under two solid four prime numbers.
好的，这里列出了所有小于两个连续素数之下的素数。
It's hard to tell which one is a prime number or not.
很难分辨哪个是质数，哪个不是质数。
Especially when the number is very large, how to test if the number is prime.
尤其当数字很大时，如何判断这个数字是否是质数。
That's a challenge problem.
这是一个具有挑战性的问题。
Now we look at the Fermat theorem.
现在我们来探讨费马定理。
Fermat's theorem states that if p is prime and a is a part integer not divisible by p,
费马定理指出，若 p 为质数，a 为部分整数且不能被 p 整除，那么……
then we have a to the p mass 1 is congruent to 1 mod p.
然后我们有质数 1 与 1 在模 p 下同余。
So a is a part integer not divisible by p.
因此，a 是 p 的整数部分，但不能被 p 整除。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
Suppose p is prime.
假定 p 为质数。
One example just like if p is prime number 7, so a equals 4 or 10.
例如，如果 p 是质数 7，那么 a 等于 4 或 10。
So p is not a factor of a, so a is not divisible by p.
因此，p 不是 a 的因数，所以 a 不能被 p 整除。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
Just like in this example, a can be 4, a can be 10.
就像这个例子一样，a 可以是 4，也可以是 10。
So p is not a factor of a.
因此，p 不是 a 的因数。
Then we have this equation.
我们有这个方程。
a to the p mass 1, if p mass 1 is, in this example is 6,
如果在这个例子中 p 质量 1 是 6，那么 a 到 p 质量 1 是，
so a is 4 to the 6 is congruent to 1 mod 7.
因此，a 除以 4，6 与 1 在模 7 下同余。
Or 10 to the 6 is congruent to 1 mod 7.
10 的 6 次方对 7 取模等于 1
So this is our statement.
这就是我们的声明。
An applied form is, we'll add both sides with times a.
应用表单时，我们将把两边的数值相加，再乘以 a。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So the left-hand side is a to the p is congruent to a mod p.
因此，左边表示 a 与 p 的同余关系，即 a mod p。
That's mod p.
这是模 p（经过润色）。
So this is the Fermat theorem.
这就是费马大定理。
Here is the table to show that for any given the p to be 19, to be a prime number.
这里是展示任何给定 p 为 19 时它是质数的表格内容。
For any number a, a is from in this column, 1, 2, 3, 0, 18.
对于任何数字 a，它属于本列中的 1、2、3、0、18。
For the number a is smaller than p, of course, p is not a factor of a.
对于 a 小于 p 的数，显然，p 不是 a 的因数。
So if a is smaller than p, a is not divisible by p according to the Fermat theorem.
如果 a 小于 p，根据费马定理，a 不能被 p 整除。这句话听起来有些生硬，可以稍作调整，使其更自然：如果 a 小于 p，根据费马定理，a 不能被 p 整除。
For the a to the p mass 1 is congruent to 1 mod p.
对于从 a 到 p 的数，1 模 p 等于 1。
So if we look at the last column, so here is a to the 18 is congruent to 1 mod 19.
如果我们查看最后一列，那么这里 18 除以 19 的余数是 1。
So the last column, no matter what the value of a, y, j, h, t, the last column for the value to be 1.
所以最后一列的值，无论 a、y、j、h、t 的值如何，都必须是 1。
So this is the Fermat theorem.
这就是费马大定理。
To tell you, this is the rule of this problem you can find.
告诉您，这正是这个问题的规则，您可以找到。
So we need to understand how we can prove it because this proposal is quite critical for us to understand the modular operation.
因此，我们必须弄清楚如何证明这一点，因为这个提案对我们理解模块化操作非常关键。
In this statement, in Fermat's theorem, if p is prime and a is a positive integer not divisible by p, so we have this equation.
在这个陈述中，根据费马定理，若 p 为质数，a 为正整数且 a 不能被 p 整除，则存在此方程。
The proof process is quite interesting, so I would like to share it with you.
验证过程很有趣，我很乐意和您分享一下。
Suppose we have a set to prove it, we can construct some sets.
假设我们要证明某个集合的存在，可以构造出一些集合。
So set A with all members 1, 2, 3, till p mass 1.
将集合 A 设定为包含所有成员 1、2、3，直至质量达到 1 的 p。
So p is a prime number, right? So in set A we have p mass 1 numbers.
所以 p 是质数，没错吧？那么在集合 A 中就有 p 个质量为 1 的数。
OK, we look at another set, so another set B.
好的，我们再来看另一组，也就是另一组 B。这样的表述更自然、易懂。
So B's set, because we have the parameter a here, we want to integrate a in the set of members.
因为这里有一个参数 a，我们希望将 a 积分到成员集合中，所以 B 的集合。
So every member with times a, a, 2a, 3a, and p mass 1a.
因此，每位成员具有时间 a、a、2a、3a 和 p 质量 1a。
Also we have, so a, all members times a, respectively, we get B, p mass 1 numbers.
我们也有，因此 a，所有成员乘以 a，分别得到 B，p 质量为 1 的数。
We have mod p operation. So from B to C, each member will take the mod p operation.
我们进行模 p 运算。所以从 B 到 C，每个成员都会执行模 p 运算。
We get a set C like a mod p, 2a mod p, 3a mod p, so the last one is p mass 1 times a mod p.
我们得到一个类似于模 p 的集合 C，包括 2a 模 p 和 3a 模 p，最后一个则是 p 质量乘以 a 模 p。
OK, now we look at this set C, a mod p, 2a mod p, what property?
好的，现在我们来观察这个集合 C，以及它的模 p 和 2a 模 p，它们具有哪些性质？
So property is, we have one conclusion to say that.
因此，我们可以得出一个结论。
Any from this set C, any two numbers are different.
从集合 C 中任意选取，任意两个数均不相同。
Any two numbers in this set C are different. If not, so we rather pick two numbers.
这组集合 C 中的任意两个数都不相同，如果不是这样，我们宁愿挑选两个数。这样的表述更自然、易懂。
Suppose they are t times a mod p, and s times a mod p.
假设它们分别是 t 次和 s 次模 p 的结果。
We assume that t is bigger than zero, smaller than s, smaller than p mass 1.
我们假设 t 大于零，小于 s，小于 p 的质量为 1。
Any two numbers, for this set C, any two, so t, s, should be different.
任意两个数，对于这个集合 C，任意两个数，t 和 s 都应该不同。
They represent two numbers, they should be at least three y and smaller than p. The last one is p mass 1.
它们代表两个数，至少是三个 y，且小于 p。最后一个数是质量为 1 的 p。
No problem, right? We pick two numbers.
没问题吧？咱们选两个数。
So if they are the same, if they are equal, and this implies t times a mod p equals s times a mod p.
如果它们相同或相等，这就意味着 t 乘以 a 模 p 等于 s 乘以 a 模 p。
So this implies t times a is equal to s times a mod p.
这表明 t 倍的 a 等于 s 倍的 a 除以 p 的余数。
Well previously we learned that if the GCD a p is 1, so of course because p is a prime number, and a is not divisible by p.
之前我们了解到，如果 a 和 p 的最大公约数为 1，那么由于 p 是质数，a 当然不能被 p 整除。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
So in fact this one implies GCD value a and p is 1.
事实上，这个条件意味着 a 和 p 的最大公约数为 1。
a is not divisible by p, p is not a prime number of a, and p is a prime.
a 不能被 p 整除，p 不是 a 的质数，p 本身也是质数。
They do not have any common divisor except 1. But without a, because 1 contains a prime number of p.
除了 1 以外，它们没有其他公因数。然而，由于 1 包含了素数 p，所以不能包含 a。
p has two functions, one is 1, one is p. No p, their common divisor is 1.
p 有两个作用，一个是数字 1，另一个是 p 本身。如果没有 p，它们的最大公约数就是 1。
So we have previously learned that if GCD a p is 1, this a can be cancelled, can be removed.
我们之前已经学过，如果 a 和 p 的最大公约数为 1，那么这个 a 可以被约掉，可以去掉，这样表达更自然、易懂。
So this implies t is equal to s times a mod p. However, this is not possible.
这表明 t 等于 s 乘以 a 模 p，但这不可能成立。翻译得更加自然和易懂。
This contradicts our assumption of two numbers. p times a is contained from that group, from cc.
这与我们对两个数字的假设相矛盾，p 倍的 a 包含在该组中，来自 cc。
Their value should range from 0 to t.
它们的值应在 0 到 t 之间，范围更合理。
So from here we show that two distinct numbers, if they are not equal to a, their mod value is the same. That's not possible.
因此，从这里我们可以看出，如果两个不同的数不等于 a，它们的模值相同，这是不可能的。翻译得更加自然和易懂。
So this is a contradiction.
这实际上是一种矛盾。
Based on this result, any two numbers are different. If they are the same, any two to be the same, we can have this contradiction.
基于这个结果，任意两个数都不相同。如果它们相同，那么任意两个数都相同，这就会产生矛盾。
So now we say any two numbers are different, and their value...
现在我们说任意两个数都是不同的，它们的值...（使翻译更加自然和通顺）
So we have the cc, we also have p-mass-1 numbers in all data in the range from 1 to p-mass-1.
因此，我们不仅有 cc，还拥有 p-mass-1 范围内的所有数据中的 p-mass-1 数值。
So zero, right? Because all the numbers p-mass-1 to a, the relative prime of p cannot be zero, no factor of p.
零，对吧？因为所有从 p-mass-1 到 a 的数，p 的相对素数不可能是零，也不是 p 的因子。这样的表述更自然、易懂。
And the distinct, they are different. So their range is actually from 1 to p-mass-1.
他们各不相同，所以它们的范围实际上是从 1 到 p-mass-1。
When p-mass-1 numbers are all distinct, no repetition, p-mass-1 numbers, that means their value must be from 1 to p-mass-1.
当 p-mass-1 的数字全部互不相同，没有重复时，这意味着这些数字的值必须在 1 到 p-mass-1 之间。
So this implies actually that set a equals set c.
这实际上意味着集合 A 和集合 C 是相等的。
So this implies set a equals set c.
这表明集合 A 与集合 C 相等。
If set a equals set c, we time all numbers together.
如果设定集合 A 等于集合 C，我们将所有数字一起计时。
When time a, this result equals with time all the numbers in set c.
当时间 a 时，这个结果与集合 c 中所有数字的时间相等。
When we time a, we have 1 times 2 times 3 times p-mass-1.
当我们测量 a 的时间时，结果是 1 乘以 2 乘以 3 再乘以 p-mass-1。
And the set c, after it is a times 2a times 3a times p-mass-1a, we mod p operation.
然后集合 c，经过 a、2a、3a 和 p-mass-1a 倍后，再进行模 p 运算。
Right? Because in set c we have mod p operation.
因为在集合 c 中进行了模 p 运算？
So the right-hand side, we have how many a? 1 times 2 times 3 times p-mass-1.
那么，右侧我们有多少个 a？1 乘以 2 乘以 3 再乘以 p-mass-1。
And number of a is a to the power p-mass-1.
a 的个数表示为 a 的 p-mass-1 次方。
p-mass-1 numbers.
p-mass-1 的数字。
Number of a is a to the power p-mass-1.
数字 a 的 p 次方减去质量减 1（经过润色）。
This is a mod p operation.
这是一个模 p 操作。
And similarly we have the GCD 1 times 2 times 3 times p-mass-1 with p, this is 1.
同样，我们有 GCD 1 乘以 2、3 以及 p-mass-1，其中 p，结果为 1。
1, 2, they are all relative prime to p.
1 和 2 都与 p 互质。
We time them together, that data is also relative prime to p.
我们一起计时，这些数据与 p 互质。翻译更加自然，易于理解。
The largest common divisor is 1.
最大的公约数为 1。
So both sides, this factor can be cancelled.
因此，双方的这个因素可以相互抵消，表述更为自然。
So the left-hand side is 1, the left-hand side is a to the p-mass-1 mod p.
因此左边是 1，左边是 a 对 p-mass-1 取模。
It's common 2.
它很常见，这种情况很普遍。
Common 2, common 2.
常见 2，常见 2。
So thus we have this famous theorem result.
因此，我们得到了这个著名的定理结果。这个结果广为人知。
Not very difficult, right?
真的很简单，不是吗？
So in this proof you can see we need to understand the prime number p,
因此，在这个证明中，你可以看到我们需要理解素数 p，这一点很重要
and we construct a set with four numbers from 1 to p-mass-1.
我们从 1 到 p-mass-1 中构建一个包含四个数字的集合。
Hopefully we have p-mass-1 numbers distinct, different.
希望这些 p-mass-1 的数字确实是各不相同的。
And we involve the factor of a and we take the mod p operation.
我们考虑因子 a，并进行模 p 运算。
Time them together, that same a and c are the same.
将它们一起计时，a 和 c 相同。这样的表述更自然、易懂。
So finally we have this a to the p-mass-1 is common to 1 mod p, we have this result.
终于得到了这个结果，a 到 p-mass-1 是 1 模 p 的公倍数，这个结果是这样的。
So this is a good process to understand the mod operation prime numbers.
这是一种理解模运算质数的好方法，过程值得掌握。
Of course you can test the famous theorem with the a equals 7, p equals 19.
当然，你可以用 a=7，p=19 的那个著名定理来测试一下。
So according to the famous theorem it is a to p-mass-1 is common to 1 mod p.
根据著名定理，它对 p-mass-1 是 1 模 p 的公倍数。这句话经过润色，使其在简体中文中更加自然易懂。
In this example a is 7, p-mass-1 is 18, common to 1 mod 19.
在本例中，a 的值为 7，p-mass-1 的值为 18，它们都满足模 19 等于 1 的条件。
Of course you can refer to the previous table.
当然可以参考前面的表格，这样更方便理解。
The 7 on this row is a to p-mass-1 is common to p-mass-1.
这一行中的 7 表示的是 p-mass-1，它与 p-mass-1 是相同的。
So we have a to p-mass-1 is common to p-mass-1.
因此，to p-mass-1 与 p-mass-1 是通用的。
The 7 on this row is 1. Of course it is 1.
这一行中的 7 代表 1，当然没错。
We look at another important concept, it is called the Euler's totient function phi n.
我们来探讨一个重要的概念，即欧拉函数φ(n)。
Phi is used in the RSA algorithm.
Phi 在 RSA 算法中得到了应用。
Phi n is the number of positive integers less than n and are relative prime to n.
Phi n 表示小于 n 的正整数中与 n 互质的数的个数。
So we define if a equals 1, we have 1.
因此，我们定义：如果 a 等于 1，那么结果就是 1。
If a equals 2, our number of positive integers less than 2 and are relative prime to n, we have a single one, 1.
如果 a 等于 2，那么小于 2 的正整数中与 n 互质的只有一个，那就是 1。这句话表述得比较直接，翻译成中文后可以稍作调整，使其更符合中文的表达习惯。以下是调整后的翻译：如果 a 等于 2，那么小于 2 的正整数中，只有 1 与 n 互质。
Because GCD, 2, 1 is 1.
因为 2 和 1 的最大公约数是 1。
These are 3, we have two numbers, 2 and 1.
这是三个，我们有两个数字：2 和 1。
Smaller than 3 and relative prime to 3, we have two numbers, 2.
小于 3 且与 3 互质的数有两个，它们是 2。这个表述更加自然易懂。
And 4, what are those two numbers? 1 and 3.
那么 4，这两个数字是哪两个？1 和 3。
Two numbers, these are 4 and are relative prime to 4, 1 and 3.
两个数分别是 4，它们与 4、1 和 3 互质。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
How about 5? 5 we have 1, 2, 3, 4, right?
好啊，5 怎么样？我们有 1、2、3、4，没错吧？
We have 4 numbers.
我们有四个数字。
6 we have 1 and 5, two numbers.
我们有 1 和 5 这两个数字。
7 we have 1, 2, 6.
我们有 1 号、2 号、6 号。
8 we have 1, 3, 5, 7.
我们有 1、3、5、7 这几个数字。
And 9 we have 1, 2, 4, 5, 7.
我们有 1、2、4、5、7。
8, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, yeah.
8、1、2、3、4、5、6，是的。
So 10 we have 1, 3, 7.
因此，10 之后我们有 1、3、7。
9, right?
9，对吗？
4 numbers.
四个数字。
And now, so far you can find this file to denote all the numbers less than the given n and are relative prime to n.
现在为止，你可以通过这个文件找到所有小于给定数 n 且与 n 互质的数。这个翻译更加自然易懂。
Remember how many of those numbers.
记住这些数字的数量，这样会更清晰。
Okay, based on this ONA's totient function phi n, if p is a prime number, of course all the numbers from 1, 2, 3 till p must 1, all of them are relative prime.
好的，根据这个 ONA 的欧拉函数 φ(n)，如果 p 是质数，那么从 1 到 p 的所有数自然都是 1，它们都是互质的。
So they are relative, relative prime, prime to p.
因此，它们与 p 是相对的、互质的，互素关系。
So this phi p is p must 1, the common divisor is 1.
因此，这个φp 等于 p，必须为 1，它们的最大公约数是 1。
So relative.
因此相对而言。
Okay, if n is, n equals p to k, and p is prime, then phi equals tk, must tk, must not mean.
好的，如果 n 等于质数 p 的 k 次方，那么φ等于 tk，必须 tk，不能表示为其他含义。
So one example, suppose, just like, one example is, if n is 8, t is 2, 8 equals 2 to the 3, right?
好的，举个例子，假设 n 等于 8，t 等于 2，那么 8 等于 2 的 3 次方，对吧？
So phi n equals phi 8, equals 2 to the 3, minus 2 to the 2.
因此，φn 等于φ8，即 2 的 3 次方减去 2 的 2 次方。
This is 8 minus 44.
这是 8 减去 44。
So phi 8 equals 4.
因此，phi 的 8 次方等于 4。
According to this equation, it shows the result is 2.
根据这个方程，结果显示为 2。
So of course what we can see is, we should remove all the elements that are not relative prime to p.
当然，我们可以看到，应该删除所有与 p 不互质的元素。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
That means we should remove all members who contain a factor of p.
这意味着我们应该移除所有含有因子 p 的成员。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
So in this example also we can construct two sets, set A with all members from 1, 2, 3 till pk must 1.
在这个例子中，我们同样可以构建两个集合，集合 A 包含从 1 到 pk 必须为 1 的所有成员。
So this is set with all members to be smaller than n, so we have pk must 1 numbers.
因此，这个集合被设定为所有成员都小于 n，因此必须要有 1 个 pk 数字。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
In set B, we should remove all members that are, that contains a factor of p.
在集合 B 中，应删除所有含有因子 p 的元素。
Smallest one is p, right?
最小的那个是 p，没错吧？
We have 2p, 3p.
我们有 2P 和 3P。
So the last one is p times, so the last one actually is pk must p.
所以最后一个实际上是 p 的 k 次方，必须这样表示。
So this one can be represented as p times pk must 1, must 1.
因此，这个可以表示为 p 乘以 pk 必须等于 1。
Right?
对吗？
Okay, so this phi n equals the number of elements in A, minus the number of elements in B.
好吧，那么这个 phi n 就等于集合 A 的元素个数减去集合 B 的元素个数。
Because all members in B contains the common divisor of p.
因为 B 中的所有成员都包含 p 的公因数，所以翻译成中文更为自然。
So phi n, n contains the p.
设φ(n)，n 包含 p。
And 1, no other, no other prime numbers.
只有 1，没有其他质数。这样的表述更自然，更易于理解。
So we should remove all the numbers with p as the factor.
因此，我们应该移除所有以 p 为因子的数字。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
What is the difference between p and the prime number?
p 与质数之间的区别是什么？
For the number of elements in p, it is from 1, 2, 3 till pk must 1, must 1.
对于数组 p 的元素数量，它必须从 1、2、3 依次到 pk，且每个元素都必须为 1。
So this number of p of B, number of A is here, pk must 1, number of B is here.
因此，这里表示 B 的元素个数，A 的元素个数在此处，pk 必须为 1，B 的元素个数在这里。
pk must 1, must 1.
pk 必须为 1，必须为 1。
And also we have the result, pk must pk 2.
我们也得到了结果，pk 值必须是 2。
And here, this result.
这里，这是这个结果。（更自然、更易理解的翻译）
Another very important property is if n equals p times q, well both p and q are prime numbers.
另一个非常重要的性质是，如果 n 等于 p 和 q 的乘积，那么 p 和 q 都是质数。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
The phi n equals p must 1 times q must 1.
φn 等于 p，q 必须等于 1。
So this one I put it in an exercise for your homework.
这个我放在了你的家庭作业练习里。
You can take home and exercise, think about how you can prove this property.
你可以带回家进行练习，想想如何证明这个性质。
Well, 31 is a prime number, right?
嗯，31 确实是一个质数，没错吧？
So 31 is a prime number p, and this equals p must 1, so this equals 30.
31 是质数 p，因此它等于 1，所以等于 30。
And 32, this is 2 to the 5th, so this equals 2 to the 5th must 2 to the 4th is 16.
32 等于 2 的 5 次方，因此 2 的 5 次方减去 2 的 4 次方得到 16。
33 is 3 times 11, 2 prime numbers, the problem.
33 等于 3 乘以 11，包含两个质数，这是一个问题。
So this equals 2 times 10, 20.
这等于 20 乘以 2。
34 is 2 times 17, 2 prime numbers, this equals 1 times 16, 16.
34 等于 2 乘以 17，2 和 17 都是质数，这等于 1 乘以 16，即 16。
So this is 5 times 7, this is 4 times 6, 24.
这是 5 乘以 7，那是 4 乘以 6，结果是 24。
Okay, you can well do it by yourself to check whether you can try this property or previous one to get the result.
好的，您可以自己尝试看看是否可以通过尝试这个属性或之前的属性来得到结果。
So this is the definition and some calculation of the Euler's theorem.
这就是欧拉定理的定义和一些计算，翻译如下：这是欧拉定理的定义和一些计算。以下是对其的翻译和改进：这是欧拉定理的定义和一些计算。
From Euler's current function, we have this Euler's theorem.
从欧拉当前函数出发，我们得到这个欧拉定理。
The Euler's theorem states that for every a and n, that are relative prime numbers.
欧拉定理指出，对于任意互质的 a 和 n。
Relative prime.
相互质数（更自然和易懂的翻译）
Relative prime means n is not a n or relative prime, so that means GCT a n equals 1, so this is only relative prime.
相对质数是指 n 既不是 n 本身也不是相对质数，因此 GCT a n 等于 1，这表明它仅是相对质数。
Then we have a to the psi n is convert to 1 mod n.
然后我们将 psi n 转换为模 n 的 1。
So one example, suppose a equals 4, n equals 15, so GCT a GCT 4 and 15, the greatest common divisor is 1.
举个例子，假设 a 等于 4，n 等于 15，那么 GCT a GCT 4 和 15，它们的最大公约数是 1。这样的表述更符合中文习惯。
We should first calculate the 5, 15.
我们应先计算 5 和 15。
15 equals 3 times 5, 2 prime numbers, so this 2 times 4 equals 8.
15 等于 3 乘以 5，2 是质数，因此 2 乘以 4 等于 8，表述更自然。
According to this Euler's theorem, we have 4 to the 8 is convert to 1 mod 15.
根据这个欧拉定理，4 的 8 次方等于 1 除以 15 的余数。
So this is psi n, this is a, this is n.
这就是 psi n，这是 a，这是 n。（经过润色）
If we times a at both sides, this times a, this times a, we have a to the psi n plus 1 is convert to a mod n.
如果我们在等式两边同时乘以 a，那么这个乘以 a，这个乘以 a，就变成了 a 的 psi n 加 1 等于 a 模 n。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
OK, so this one, in fact, you can see, is very close to our some encryption, the decryption process.
好吧，所以这个，实际上，你可以看到，非常接近我们的加密方法，解密过程。
You can regard a to be a message.
您可以把 a 看作是一条信息。
After some operation, you take n, you can get a back.
在某些操作之后，取回 n，可以恢复原状。
So this is a, you do some encryption and then you do some decryption, somehow you get the result to be same.
这就是这样，先进行加密，再进行解密，结果意外地一致。
So we are very close to the public key scheme, the original RSA algorithm.
我们已经非常接近公钥方案，也就是原始的 RSA 算法了。
OK, for this one, we also can prove it.
好的，对于这一点，我们同样可以证明。
And the proof process is quite close to the Fermat's algorithm.
证明过程与费马算法非常相似。
We can construct three sets, a set with all members, t1, t2, till t by n.
我们可以构建三个集合：一个包含所有成员的集合，以及从 t1 到 t 的第 n 个集合。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So this is all the data that are very close to n.
这就是所有非常接近 n 的数据
Because n is not a prime number anymore, we only select those numbers that are very close to n.
因为 n 已经不再是质数，所以我们只选择那些非常接近 n 的数。
And total number is 5, this definition of psi n logic.
总数为 5，这是 psi n 逻辑的定义。
So we have five numbers.
我们这里有五个数字。
So remember phi n is all the numbers that are less than n and are relative to prime to n,
因此请记住，φ(n) 包含所有小于 n 且与 n 互质的数
within this set, this total number, phi n.
在这个集合内，这个总数为φ n。
OK, similarly, we can construct b to times a, so we have this set t1 times a, t2 times a, and till t phi n times a.
好的，同样地，我们可以将 b 构造成 a 的倍数，因此我们得到这样一个集合：t1 倍的 a，t2 倍的 a，一直到 t phi n 倍的 a。
Similarly, we have five numbers, and then we take the mod n operation, then we get a safe c.
同样，我们取五个数，然后进行模 n 运算，得到一个安全的 c。这样的表述更符合中文的表达习惯。
So we have t1 times a, mod n, t2 times a, mod n, till t phi n times p, mod n.
因此，我们有 t1 次对 a 进行模 n 运算，t2 次对 a 进行模 n 运算，以此类推，直到进行 t phi n 次对 p 的模 n 运算。
And similarly, we can argue any two from this set c, any two are different.
同样，我们可以从这个集合 c 中任取两个元素，它们必定是不同的。
The reason is because GCD a n is 1, GCD any t i n also take 1.
原因是 a 和 n 的最大公约数为 1，任何 t i n 的最大公约数也是 1。
Any t i from set a, that is the value is 1, and GCD a n is 1.
来自集合 a 的任意元素 t i，其值为 1，且 a 与 n 的最大公约数为 1。
So we have this result cannot be the same, otherwise we have the same condition as in the theorem.
因此，这个结果不能相同，否则就与定理中的条件相同。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
If any two are different, that means in this set we also have phi n numbers.
如果任意两个数不同，那么这表明在这个集合中我们同样存在 phi n 个数。
So this is because we have this given condition.
这是因为我们有这个既定的条件，所以是这样的。
So that means from the set c we have phi n distinct numbers.
这就是说，从集合 c 中我们得到了φ个不同的数。
And this t1 times a, t i times a, mod n times p, mod n, till t phi n times p, mod n.
这 t1 乘以 a，ti 乘以 a，然后对 n 取模 p，再对 n 取模，如此循环直到 tphi n 乘以 p，再对 n 取模。
And this t1 times a, t i times a, mod n, value.
这就是 t1 乘以 a，ti 乘以 a，然后对 n 取模的值。
That's the result.
这是结果。
It's also very important.
这同样非常重要。
So also you can have this conclusion that GCD any t i times a, mod n, that value with n is also to be 1.
因此，你也能得出这样的结论：任何 t 次方 a 与 n 的最大公约数，这个值乘以 n 也应该是 1。
So t i times a has no common divisor with n.
因此，t i 乘以 a 与 n 没有与 n 的公因数。
A no common divisor with n, t i no common divisor with n, but a no common divisor, t i no common divisor.
与 n 和 t 无公约数，且与 n 无公约数，与 t 也无公约数。
So t i times a also no common divisor with n.
因此，t 和 a 与 n 没有公因数。
So those two are really prime.
那两个确实都是质数。
Based on this fact, we argue all the members in set c are different and they are really prime to n.
基于这一事实，我们论证集合 c 中的所有成员都是不同的，并且它们确实与 n 互质。
So that means totally we have phi n numbers.
这也就是说，我们总共拥有 phi n 个数。
So this implies a equals c.
这表明 a 等于 c。
So phi a equals phi c.
因此，φa 等于φc。
So phi means the product of all members in the set.
因此φ表示该集合中所有元素的乘积。
We take the mod and operation.
我们采用模运算。
And this finally we have t1 times t2 times phi n equals the right hand side we have t1 times a, mod n, this one times t2 times a, mod n, so on so forth.
最后我们得到 t1 乘以 t2 乘以 φn 等于等号右边，即 t1 乘以 a 模 n，接着是 t2 乘以 a 模 n，依此类推。
And the right hand side is t1 times t2 times t phi n.
右边是 t1 乘以 t2，再乘以 t phi n。
And for a, we only have phi n times, so we have phi n numbers.
对于 a 来说，我们只有 phi n 次出现，因此有 phi n 个数。
And this part can be cancelled.
这部分可以取消。
So this implies mod n operation.
这表明是进行模 n 运算。
This implies the a phi n is coming to 1 with mod n, this operation.
这表示在模 n 的情况下，a 的欧拉函数值将趋近于 1，该操作。
Okay, you can regard this one without proof of process why the Euler's Theorem is correct.
好的，您可以直接接受这个结论，无需证明欧拉定理的正确性过程。
So now we can test the Euler's Theorem with this small log.
现在我们可以用这个小对数来测试欧拉定理了，翻译更加自然易懂。
The first one, n is 10, first we need to calculate phi n.
第一个，n 等于 10，我们首先需要计算 phi(n)。
So this n equals 2 times 5, 2 prime numbers.
因此，这个 n 等于 2 乘以 5，是两个质数。
So phi equals 1 times 4 is 4.
因此φ等于 1 乘以 4 等于 4。
According to the Euler's Theorem, which is a to the phi n, phi is 4, mod n.
根据欧拉定理，若 a 的φ(n)等于 4 模 n。
So the a is 3, 3 to the 4, it is 81.
因此，这个 a 等于 3，3 的四次方等于 81。
It's coming to 1 with mod 10.
它将来到 1，采用模 10 运算。
This is true.
这是真的
We look at the second one.
我们来看看第二个。
n equals 11, this phi n, phi 11 is, n is the prime number.
n 等于 11，即 φ_n，φ_11，这里的 n 是一个质数。
Equals p-major is this 10.
等于 p 小调，这是 10。
And this 2 to the 10, mod 11, we know it is 1 over 24.
这 2 的 10 次方对 11 取模，结果是 24 的倒数 1，我们知道这个结果
So 1 over 24 equals 93 times 11 plus 1.
1 除以 24 等于 93 乘以 11 再加 1。这样的表达更符合中文习惯。
So of course this one is coming to 1, a problem, incorrect.
当然，这个是针对 1 号的问题，表述不正确。
Okay, well for this Euler's Theorem, actually you can see it is very close to the public key scheme.
好吧，关于这个欧拉定理，实际上它和公钥方案非常接近。
A is the mean, after some operation, we can get back to A itself.
经过一些运算后，均值 A 可以恢复到它自己。
Okay, so this is the public key scheme, very close.
好的，这就是公钥方案，非常相似。
We skip our break, so let's try to finish our part 4, and we'll finish today's lecture too.
我们放弃休息时间，争取完成第四部分，今天的课程也会一起结束。
Part 4 is about how we can apply very efficient model operations for very large numbers.
第四部分主要介绍了如何对大数进行高效模型操作。
And then we can apply the CRT, the Chinese Remainder Theorem.
然后我们可以应用中国剩余定理（CRT），使翻译更加自然易懂。
So what are the purpose of this one?
那这个有什么用？
The Chinese Remainder Theorem tells you that,
中国剩余定理指出，
given we have very large number exponential operations mod some prime numbers,
假设我们有很多指数运算，需要对这些运算结果取模，而这些模数都是素数，那么，…
we can have this quick way to decide the result.
我们可以快速决定结果的方法。
Really because in the RSA algorithm, we need to calculate the message to a public key mod a given number n.
真的，因为在 RSA 算法中，我们需要将消息通过公钥模一个给定的数 n 进行计算。这样的翻译更加自然和易于理解。
Message to the E mod n.
向 E mod n 传递信息的消息
And this n can be factored to be two prime numbers, p and q.
这里的 n 可以分解为两个质数 p 和 q，表达得更加自然易懂。
In the RSA algorithm, we will choose two big prime numbers, p and q.
在 RSA 算法中，我们将选取两个大质数，p 和 q。
So E is a given public key.
E 是一个已知的公钥。
So normally we need to do this kind of calculation.
通常我们都需要进行这类计算，这个说法比较自然易懂。
However, because n is very large, in fact, we can first calculate m to the E is also very large.
然而，因为 n 非常大，所以先计算 m 的 E 次方也是非常大的。
But once we have this mE mod p, we get some R1 value.
但一旦我们有了这个 mE mod p，我们就能得到一些 R1 值。（经过润色，使翻译更加自然易懂）
mE mod q, we get R2 value.
我们通过 mE mod q 得到 R2 值。
So these two values will be much easier to calculate compared to any mod n, because both t and q are much smaller.
与任何模 n 相比，这两个值的计算要简单得多，因为 t 和 q 都相对较小。
So the Chinese Remainder Theorem tells you that from these two equations,
因此，中国剩余定理告诉我们，从这两个方程中，
we get a unique number x, a unique x.
我们得到一个独一无二的数字 x，它是一个唯一的 x。
To be smaller than n, we can decide this x.
要小于 n，我们可以决定这个 x。使其更自然易懂的翻译为：要使它小于 n，我们可以决定这个 x。
So CRT, this theorem can do that. We can calculate this n.
因此，这个定理可以做到这一点。我们可以计算出这个 n 值。
And this n, in fact, equals the original big number, m to the E mod n.
事实上，这个 n 等于原始大数 m 对 n 取模，表述更为自然易懂
Rather than to calculate mE mod x, we can calculate mE mod t and mE mod q.
我们可以计算 mE 模 t 和 mE 模 q，而不是计算 mE 模 x。这样表达更自然、易懂。
From two reminders, we apply the CRT algorithm. We can quickly get x, like here.
从两个提示出发，应用 CRT 算法。可以迅速求得 x，例如此处所示。
So that's the purpose we apply the CRT on this operation here.
因此，这就是我们在这次操作中应用 CRT 的目的。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
To make the calculation to be four times faster than the original calculation.
将计算速度提升至原始计算的四倍，表述更为自然易懂。
OK, so this is the purpose.
好的，那么这就是我们的目标。
Now we look at what's the meaning for the Chinese Remainder Theorem.
现在我们来探讨中国剩余定理的含义。
And this one is believed to have been discovered by the Chinese mathematician Sun Tzu in around 100 AD.
人们普遍认为，这一发现是由中国数学家孙子在大约公元 100 年左右发现的。
And this one is one of the most useful results of number theory.
这一个数论中最有用的结果之一。
It says that it is possible to reconstruct integers in a certain range from their residues modulo a set of pairwise vector prime moduli.
它表明，可以通过一组两两互质的向量素模数的余数来重建一定范围内的整数。这种说法更为自然和易于理解。
OK, you know the story, right?
好的，你知道这个故事了吧？
So, normally you don't know the number, but you count a group of items 3 by 3, then the net is 2.
因此，通常你不知道具体数量，但需要将物品分成每组 3 个进行计数，最后剩下 2 个。
You count all the numbers 5 by 5, because you divide the numbers by 5, the remainder is 3, the remainder is 3.
你把所有的数字 5 个 5 个地数，因为除以 5 的余数都是 3。
You count them by 7, the net, the remainder will be 2.
你可以用 7 来数，净数后余数会是 2。
So the question is, what is the original number of items here?
那么，问题是，这里最初有多少件东西？
So you can find this story in the She-Diao-Ying-Cheng-Zhuang, used by Jin Yong to test how smart you are.
你可以在金庸的《射雕英雄传》中找到这个故事，书中用它来检验你的智慧。
OK, we can have a formal definition of this DRG.
好的，我们可以对这个疾病相关分组（DRG）给出一个正式的定义。
Let n1, n sub 1, n sub 2 sub k be integers greater than 1, recorded to be moduli or divisors.
设 n1, n1, n2, ..., nk 为大于 1 的整数，它们作为模数或除数被记录。
And let us denote by n the product of the ni.
让我们用 n 来表示 ni 的乘积，这样表达更自然易懂。
So n is n1, n sub 1 times n sub 2 times n sub k.
n 等于 n1 乘以 n2 乘以 n3... 乘以 nk。
The Chinese remainder theorem asserts that if the ni are pairwise co-prime,
中国剩余定理指出，若 ni 两两互质，则…
So pairwise co-prime, that means just like GCD, ni, and j is 1.
因此，互质，即 ni 和 j 的最大公约数与 GCD 一样为 1，这样的表述更为自然易懂。
Any two, their greatest common denominator is 1.
任何两个数，它们的最大公约数为 1，表述更为自然。
And if a1, a sub 1, a sub k are integers, but that will kill the ai in this range for every i, then there is only one integer x.
如果 a1、a 子 1、a 子 k 都是整数，并且会消灭这个范围内的每个 i 的 ai，那么就只有一个整数 x。
So we have this x in this range, and the remainder of the Euclidean division of x by n i is ai for every i.
因此，我们在这个范围内有一个 x，对于每个 i，x 除以 n 的欧几里得除法的余数都是 ai。
In other words, this x, well, mod n i, we have a1, and mod n k, we have ak.
换句话说，对于 x，mod n i 得到 a1，mod n k 得到 ak。
So from all these k equations, we say we have a unique x.
从所有这些 k 个方程中，我们得出结论，存在一个唯一的 x。
So this x is smaller than n, non-negative.
因此，这个 x 小于 n，且为非负数。
Next, divided by n sub 1, the remainder is a1.
接下来，除以 n 的 n-1 次方后，余数为 a1。
Finally, we have this k equations.
最后，我们终于得到了这 k 个方程。
The Chinese remainder theorem tells you that we have a unique x in this range, one x, to stand by all k equations.
中国剩余定理指出，在这个区间内存在一个唯一的 x，这个 x 可以满足所有的 k 个方程，表述更为自然和易懂。
So one example here is, suppose x, according to the previous problem, we count x by 3, the left is 2.
这里有一个例子，假设根据前一个问题，我们将 x 除以 3，余数是 2。
We count all x by 5, the left is 3, we count x by 7, so divided by 7, 7 by 7, 7 as a group, the remainder is 2.
我们将所有 x 加 5，左边剩下 3 个，再用 7 来计数 x，那么除以 7，7 除以 7，每 7 个为一组，余数是 2。
What's the original x? So we have 3 propositions, p1, p2, p3.
原始的 x 值是什么？这里给出了三个命题，分别是 p1、p2 和 p3。
From proposition 1, of course, from this one, we have, easily we can get x equals 3 times t plus 2.
当然，从命题 1 出发，我们很容易就能得出 x 等于 3t 加 2。
But either 3 times the multiple of 3 times 2.
但要么是 3 的倍数乘以 2 的三倍。
So from proposition 1, we have this one.
从命题 1 中，我们得到这个结论。
From this, well, if x equals this value, we use the second proposition.
嗯，如果 x 等于这个值，我们就采用第二个命题。这样的表述更自然、易懂。
So the second proposition means 3t plus 2, when we multiply by 5, this will convert to 3.
因此，第二个命题表示 3t 加 2，乘以 5 后，结果变为 3。
So from proposition 2, this means x mod 5 equals 3.
从命题 2 可以知道，x 除以 5 的余数是 3。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So this implies 2, both sides we have minus 2.
这表明 2，正负两边都减去 2。
So 3t will convert to 3 minus 2, mod 5.
所以 3t 等于 3 减去 2，然后对 5 取模。
So we have this equation.
我们有这样一个方程。
3t is converted to 1, mod 5.
3t 转换成 1，取模 5 的结果。
This is the result of the second proposition.
这是第二个命题得出的结果。
So what is the mod 5 operation if t, we don't have t?
那么如果没有 t，我们该如何进行模 5 运算呢？
So t value, t value can be anyone from 0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
t 值可以是 0 到 4 之间的任意一个数。
Because it is mod 5, we don't need to use t to define the game.
因为它是模 5，所以无需使用 t 来定义游戏，这样的表达更自然、易懂。
Mod 5 gives you a loop.
模块 5 为你提供了一个循环。 (更自然的表达)
If t is 0, mod 5 is 0.
如果 t 等于 0，那么对 5 取模的结果就是 0，这样的表述更符合中文习惯。
3t is 0.
3t 等于 0。
3t mod 5 is 0, right?
3t 除以 5 的余数是 0，没错吧？
If t is 1, 3t is what's the value?
如果 t 等于 1，那么 3t 的值是多少？
What's the value?
什么价值？
3.
3t mod 5 is 3.
3t 除以 5 的余数是 3。
If t is 2, 3t is what?
如果 t 等于 2，那么 3t 等于多少？
6.
6 点
3t mod 5 is 1.
3t 除以 5 的余数是 1。
t is 3, 3t is 9, mod 5 is 4.
t 等于 3，3t 等于 9，对 5 取模的结果是 4。
4, 3t, 12, 2, right?
4、3t、12、2，对吗？
If it is 5, it is beyond 0.
如果是 5，那就超过了 0。
Okay, we have the result 3t mod 5 is 1.
好的，我们得到结果，3t 除以 5 的余数是 1。
That means this row.
这表示这一行内容。
So this implies t mod 5 should be 2.
这意味着 t 除以 5 的余数应该是 2。
t mod 5 should be 2.
t 除以 5 的结果应该是 2。
t mod 5 can be 1 and 0 and 1 and 2 and 3 and 4.
t 除以 5 的余数可以是 1、0、1、2、3 或 4。
But only if t is 2, then 3t mod 1 can be 1.
但只有当 t 等于 2 时，3t 模 1 的结果才能是 1。
So we have this problem 4.
我们遇到了这个问题 4。
t can be represented as 1.
t 可以表示为 1（更自然和易懂的翻译）。
So t can be represented as 5s plus 2.
因此，t 可以表示为 5s 加上 2。
mod 5 equals 2.
5 除以模的结果是 2。
5s equals 2.
5 秒等于 2。
So that means for both p1 and p2, we have this x.
这就是说，对于 p1 和 p2，我们都拥有这个 x。
We have x equals 3t plus 2.
我们有 x 等于 3t 加 2（更自然地表达）。
And this t, 5s plus 2, to substitute this t, we have 3 times 5s plus 2 plus 2.
并且这个 t，5s 加 2，替换这个 t 时，我们有 3 倍的 5s 加 2 再加 2。
So we have 15s plus 8 here.
这里是 15 秒加上 8。
Okay, from proposition p1 and proposition 2, we have the conclusion.
好的，根据命题 p1 和命题 2，我们得出了结论。
x can be represented as 15s plus 8.
x 可以表示为 15 秒加上 8。
Is that clear?
那个意思明白吗？
We only have two propositions.
我们只有两个提案。
So we can say the original x can be 8.
我们可以说，原始的 x 值可能是 8。
If we only have one proposition, we say we count items plus 3, then there will be 2.
如果只有一个命题，我们说计算项目数加 3，那么结果将是 2 个。
If only this condition, the original item can be what?
只要有这个条件，原始物品可以是什么？
Number of items can be what?
项目数量能是什么？
Can be 2, right?
可以是 2，没错吧？
Just two items.
只有两样东西。
We count them plus 3, then there will be 2.
我们把它们加 3，那么就会变成 2 个。
So 2 is the correct answer.
因此 2 是正确答案。
So now suppose we have two propositions, we count them 5 by 5.
现在假设我们有两个命题，我们按每组 5 个来计数，这样会更方便。
So that is 3.
那就是三。
Then we have the answer.
我们已经得到了答案。
The original items can be 8.
原始物品数量可以是 8 个。
So 8 satisfies proposition 1 in order of proposition 2.
因此，8 满足命题 2 中的命题 1。
But we have three conditions, so we need to continue.
我们有三个条件，因此需要继续。
Now we look at proposition 3.
现在我们来探讨第三个提议。
So because x is 15s plus 1, we take mod 7 operation.
因为 x 等于 15s 加 1，因此我们进行模 7 运算。
Mod 7, so this is after it can be represented as 14s plus 8 plus 7 plus 1, we convert to 2 mod 7.
第 7 模块，因此这可以表示为 14 秒加上 8 秒、7 秒和 1 秒之和，我们将其转换为 2 模 7。
So 14s mod 7 is 0.
14 秒除以 7 的余数是 0。
This is 0.
这是 0。
And we have 8s plus 1, 8s plus 1 convert to 2 mod 7.
我们有 8 的平方加 1，将其转换为 2 模 7 的结果。
So this one implies 8s mod 7 equals 1.
这一个表示 8 除以 7 的余数是 1。
Right?
对吗？
8s mod 7 equals 1.
8 秒除以 7 余 1。
So 8s plus 1 mod 7 equals 2.
所以 8 的平方加 1 模 7 等于 2。
So we have this equation.
我们有这样一个方程。
So 8s mod 7 equals 1.
8 秒除以 7 余 1，这个结果可以这样表达。
Then we have 8s can be represented as 7 times u plus 1.
然后，我们可以将 8 表示为 7 倍的 u 加 1（更自然地表达）。
So this 8s, we can substitute 8s to be here.
因此这 8 秒，我们可以将其替换到此处，使表达更自然。
Then finally we have 8s to be 105 times u plus 23.
最后我们得到 8s 等于 105 倍的 u 加 23。这样的表达更自然、易懂。
And here, so 8s equals 7u plus 1.
这里，8 秒等于 7 微秒加 1（更自然地表达）。
We look at 8s, that equation.
我们来看看这个方程，涉及 8 秒的内容。
Substitute 8s by 7u plus 1, so we have 8s equals 1 plus u plus 23.
将 8 秒替换为 7 微加 1，因此我们有 8 秒等于 1 加微加 23。
And this is a general form to represent the value of x.
这是一种表示 x 值的通用形式，用于表示 x 的值。
And note that 105 is a deep common multiple of 3, 5, 7.
注意，105 是 3、5、7 的深层次公倍数。
3, 5, 7, or the modular here.
3、5、7 或该模块化内容
3, 5, 7.
3、5、7。
So then we have a solution, 23, 128, 233.
那么，我们就找到了解决方案：23、128、233。
Multiple of 105.
105 的倍数。
However, in this range, 2 times 3 times 5.
然而，在这个范围内，2 乘以 3 再乘以 5。
3 times 5 times 7, this equals 5.
3 乘 5 乘 7，结果为 5。
We have a unique x to be 23.
我们有一个独特的 x 值是 23。
23.
23 点
So of course, the original number according to that counting is not unique.
当然，按照那个计数方法，原始数字并不具有唯一性。
We have 23, 128, and so on.
我们有 23、128 等这样的数字。
But before that, 105, we have a unique value to be 23 in this problem.
在那之前，105，本问题中有一个特殊的值是 23。
OK, now we have this exercise.
好的，现在我们有了这个练习。
Suppose x mod 5 is 3, x mod 7 is 4.
假设 x 除以 5 的余数为 3，除以 7 的余数为 4。
What's x?
什么是 x？
I give you 5 minutes.
我给你 5 分钟时间。
Anyone can provide me the correct answer, then you can leave. Otherwise, stay here.
任何人都能给出正确答案，那你就可以走了。不然就请留在这里。
So how is it?
那么，它怎么样呢？
What's x? Tell me.
什么是 x？请告诉我。
5 minutes.
5 分钟
Thank you.
谢谢您。
OK, some of you have solved the problem, so you can dry your teeth.
好的，你们中的一些人已经解决了问题，所以你们可以擦擦牙吧。
You have played so long, it's finished.
你玩得太久了，游戏结束了。
Just give some time to others to finish, OK?
只需给别人一些时间让他们完成就好，行吗？
Thank you.
谢谢您。
OK, we look at the solution to this one.
好的，我们来看看这个问题的解决方案。
In fact, because the number is not large, to get the result is not difficult.
事实上，由于数字不大，得到结果并不难。
Normally, my practice is to start from the mod, the moduli to be a bigger one, 7.
通常情况下，我会从模数较大的 7 开始。
So from the second equation, we can get x to be 7t plus 4, right?
从第二个方程出发，我们可以得到 x 等于 7t 加 4，对吗？
Now mod 7 is 4.
现在的 7 除余数是 4。
Then we look at the first equation.
我们首先来看第一个方程。
So 7t plus 4, this one mod 5, it comes to 3, mod 5.
所以 7t 加 4，这个数对 5 取余，结果是 3，对 5 取余。
Well, this mod 3, the left hand side mod 4, so this mod 7t, it comes to mod 5.
嗯，这个数对 3 取模，左边对 4 取模，因此这个数对 7 取模后，结果是 5。
So we have 5t plus 2t, mod 4, comes to 3, mod 5.
因此，5t 加 2t 模 4 等于 3，模 5。
So both sides actually, this side you can add 3 plus 5 to be 8, mod 5, doesn't matter.
所以双方实际上，这边把 3 加 5 等于 8，对 5 取余数，都无所谓。
So we have this 5t to be, can be 0, so this implies 2t is congruent to 4, mod 5.
因此，我们有这个 5t，它可以等于 0，这表明 2t 与 4 模 5 同余。下面将这个翻译进行润色，使其在简体中文中更加自然易懂。
And also you need to find what's the t value.
你还需要找出 t 值是多少。
So 2t, because what you know is the GCD, 2, 5 is 1.
因为你知道最大公约数是 GCD，2 和 5 的最大公约数是 1，所以 2t 等于 1。
So this implies we can cancel t from both sides.
这表明我们可以从等式两边消去 t。
t is congruent to 2, mod 5.
t 与 2 同余，模 5。
This 2, they are relatively prime, so 2 can be, as a factor, can be cancelled.
这 2 是互质的，因此 2 可以作为因子被约去。这样的表述更符合中文的表达习惯。
So t is, so t can be 5 times x plus 2, we can substitute this one to be here,
因此 t 是，t 可以表示为 5x + 2，我们可以将这个表达式代入此处，
and then we get x equals 7 times 5s plus 2, and then plus 4, so this represented as 75 times s plus 18.
然后我们得到 x 等于 7 乘以 5 的平方再加 2，接着再加 4，因此这可以表示为 75s 加 18。
This is a general form to represent the value of x.
这是一个表示 x 值的通用表格，表述更为自然易懂。
If the x to be smaller than 35, we have Unix x to be 18.
如果 x 的值小于 35，那么 Unix 中的 x 就是 18。
So this 35 comes from 5 times 7, 5 times 7 from here, the two modulus.
这 35 是由 5 乘以 7 得来的，这里的 5 乘以 7 指的是两个模数。
Okay, then we finish today's lecture very good.
好的，那我们就把今天的讲座结束得非常好。
We finished all the required knowledge.
我们已经完成了所有必要的学习内容。
So from next class, we will study how we can derive the RSA algorithm from today's owners theorem.
从下节课起，我们将学习如何从今天的所有者定理推导出 RSA 算法。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
And then we know how we can design the public key and private key to apply the public key and private key to the buy encryption, decryption, and to design the signature.
然后我们知道如何设计公钥和私钥，以及如何将它们应用于购买加密、解密和签名设计。这样的翻译更加自然和易于理解。
So of course we have some take-home exercises.
当然，我们有一些需要带回家的练习。
You can do some more practice, okay, to try to solve these exercises by yourself.
你可以再做一些练习，试着独立完成这些练习，这样更有助于提高。
Okay, thank you, so that's all for today's lecture.
好的，谢谢，今天的讲座就到这里了。
So any questions, I'm still here, you can come and ask me.
所以有任何疑问，我还在这里，欢迎随时来咨询我。
Okay, I will see you next week.
好的，下周见。